Guide to the Hopkins Transportation Collection Photographs M0234
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Hopkins Transportation Collection photographs
1870-1964 (inclusive), 1877-1943 (bulk)
bulk
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
M0234
3 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
Images depicting transportation from various sources.
Scope and Content
Miscellaneous photograph collection containing accessions of original and copy prints depicting railroads, street cars, airplanes, automobiles, ships and other forms of transportation. Material was formerly part of Stanford's Hopkins Transportation Library. Images are in a variety of formats - mounted and unmounted, paper prints (possibly contacts or reprints), copy prints & negatives, etc. Collection is not limited to photographs (see Box 1 especially). Likewise, other HTL collections may also contain photos.
Of note are several albumen prints attributed to Alfred Hart's Central Pacific series (many of which appear to be variously cropped versions of negatives) as well as large photographs of a Ladies Driving Club in England. There is also a memoir about Lawrence Hargrave by A.E. Beriman, material relating to the Royal Aeronautical Society and The Early Birds of Aviation, and a piece of original fabric from the Wright Brothers plane at Kitty Hawk. Also includes railroad stock certificates, the aviation papers of Stanley H. Page, and other miscellaneous materials relating to transportation.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received from various sources.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Railroads -- History; Aeronautics -- History.; Automobiles -- History; Ships -- History
- Series 1. Railroads & street cars
  - Advertisement, Eades: Patent Differential Pulley Blocks, Sacramento, California. Huntington, Hopkins & Company, September 1880 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gould-Huntington Contract, Nov 26, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Scope and Contents
    El Paso, Texas (West) Track Agreement. Source: Hammon.
  - Pennsylvania Railroad: Ticket offices and depots of the Pennsylvania Railroad at Philadelphia., circa 1870; 2 page pamphlet. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Scope and Contents note
    (Source: Hammon)
  - Pacific Coast Steamship & Central Pacific Railroad Co. & Southern Pacific Railroad Co. & South Pacific Company contract, 1 Feb 1877, 1 Feb 1885 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Pacific Coast Steamship & Central Pacific Railroad Co. & Southern Pacific Railroad Co. & South Pacific Company: Pool Agreement - original contract, and modifications. Source: Hammon.
  - Early train stations in California (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Stock certificates: railroad, shipping, etc., 1877-1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Transfers and various sources. Includes Crocker, Huntington, other signatures.
      - 1901 Oil Company (1901 Oil Company
      - Capay Valley Land Company, (1918)
      - Central New York and Western Railroad Co., (1943)
      - Coal and products Co., (1909)
      - Colorado Steam Navigation Co., (1893)
      - El Verano Improvement Assoc., (1914, 1918)
      - El Verano Villa Assoc., (1920)
      - Fresno Land and Improvement Co., (1893)
      - Gravey Bar Dredging Co., (1910)
      - Ione Coal and Iron Co., (1890, 1893)
      - Oakland, Brooklyn and Fruitvale Rai-road Co., (1896)
      - Portland and Dambill Railroad Co., (1893)
      - Portland and Willamette Valley Railway Co., (1887)
      - San Lorenzo Flume and Transportation Co., (1877)
      - San Pedro Harbor, Dock, and Land Assoc., (1897)
      - Simmons Bar Dredging Co., (1911
      - Sonoma Valley Improvement Co., (1888, 1889, 1891)
      - Union Fuel Co., (1904, 1906)
  - Southern Pacific locomotives, gift of Mrs. Delmar Green, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Central Pacific Railroad - Alfred Hart paper prints + later negatives (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Related Materials
    While there is no original documentation, these photographs (approx. 36 4x3/4" thin paper prints) have been identified as the work of Alfred Hart, staff photographer for the Central Pacific from 1864-1868. Some images match published stereoviews by him. The majority depict trains, trestles, tracks, and mountain scenery. Several document the interiors of Pullman cars. A few have writing on their verso. Many prints appear to be variously cropped versions of single negatives.
    Stanford University Archives holds the Alfred A. Hart photographs, 1862-1869 (PC0002): http://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4085081.
  - Central Pacific snow removal album by I.W. Taber copy negatives (Box 2, Folder 4)
    The photo album itself is MSS PHOTO 407 "Central Pacific trans-Sierra line in winter: photograph album, 1890" (https://searchworks.stanford.edu/view/4084000)
  - Central Pacific Construction Deeth, Utah (Mt. Hallock in distance) Prospect Hill cut. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Central Pacific 3 Copy prints (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Central Pacific 5 photos, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Union Pacific and Central Pacific copyprints (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Western Pacific - locomotives (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Baltimore, Ohio postcards (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 24 Postcard photos - mainly Baltimore, Ohio RR (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Leona Line, RPT (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Railroad - Molino, Monte Vista (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - California - Northern Electric Railway Co. 27 photos, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Panama RR (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rhode Island Locomotive Works 6 photos of engines, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sutro Heights locomotives, later (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Locomotives Colorado 6 color pictures (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Locomotives. Great Britain postcards (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Locomotives Japan (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Street Cars - California (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Street Cars, San Francisco (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Railroads - Los Angeles, 32 line car. Los Angeles. 33 Santa Monica Los Angeles. 34 Los Angeles, San Pedro, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Glass slides - copy negatives + prints (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Eastern Bound Train Leaving Oakland Point - Houseworth [copy print], 1870s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Horsedrawn streetcars/buggies (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Railroads (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Copy prints from Loomis collection: Display of American Flag Across the Cut, Awaiting Approach of Presidential Train; Colon- Gang on Sewer Construction.; crowd of people in front of train tunnel, unidentifed location
- Series 2. Aereonautical
  - Airplane photos (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See also nitrate negative file and James Deitrick Papers - 140/1/14.
    - 1. Stanford alumni: Floyd Merritt, J.E. Brick Elliott, Pat Ferris, Jan, 1929
    - 2. Stanford alumni, geologists, May, 1929
    - 3. [Stanford alumni?]: Baker, Brandt, Schilder by a Douglas 0-32, May-30
    - 4. [Stanford alumni?] for Stanford Illustrated Review, May-30
    - 5. Six magazine clippings
      [National Geographic?], reproducing 12 photos including Lindergh and his monoplane and Byrd and his plane America.
    - 6. Roger's aereoplane photo, 1910
      Part of the Roger's aeroplane (a photo of); the first to fly across the U.S., (and descriptive letter).
  - CAA photos, 1926-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Twenty 8 × 10 black and white photos; gift of the Civil Aeronautics Administration. Information is on the back of each photo.
  - French aviation postcards (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Gift of Hermann Knoche.
    - Sports-aviation series:
      - 6. Wright, Wilbur and plane
      - 21. Warflinger and single wing Antoinette IV (see 93)
      - 23. Dumont, Santos and plane
      - 25. Farman, Henri and plane
      - 30. Aeroplane Vuia (See 101), (May 1907)
      - 33. Koecklin and plane
      - 43. Guilleband and plane in Rouen.
      - 51. Bonnet-LabrancheII
      - 54. Zens
      - 54. Colonel Coddy's plane (See 103)
      - 60. Bleriot-&-Voisin and plane
      - 63. Equevilley's multiwing plane
      - 64. Glider of M. Belin fils.
      - 66. Gilbert and plane
      - 72. M. Santos-Dumont and plane
      - 76. M. Bleriot and plane La Libellule
      - 90. M. Henri Farman and triplane
      - 91. Delagrange airplane
      - 93. Single wing Antoinette IV (see 21)
      - 97. Auffin-Ordt
      - 97. Single wing Esnault-Pelterce
      - 99. June Bug
      - 101. Vuia (see 30)
      - 102. Esnault-Pelterie
      - 103. English military plane of Colonel Cody (See 54)
      - 104. Flying machine of Laurence Lesh at Morris Park, New York.
    - Different series:
      - 12. Wilbur Wright airplane
      - 13. Wilbur Wright airplane
      - 15. Delagrange airplane
      - 16. Delagrange airplane
      - 72. Sommer airplane
      - 80. Curtiss airplane
      - 81. Bleriot airplane
      - 83. Farman airplane
      - 84. Voisin airplane
      - 85. La Demoiselle de Santos Dumont (See #23 first series).
    - Fetes de l'aviation
      - [1] M. Latham dans le prix d'altitude
      - [2] Bleriot's last flight one minute before burning
    - Parked planes
      - 60. Bi-plane
      - 64. Voisin airplane
    - Dirigibles
      - 3. Clement-Bayard
    - Italian post card: Ala Littoria
  - Early Birds of Aviation, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Papers of the Early Birds of Aviation, Inc. Includes newsclippings, correspondence, photographs, membership lists, & pamphlets. Gift of Stanley Page.
  - The Aero Manual First edition, Temple Press, Ltd., London, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gift of Stanley H. Page.
  - Magazines (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1. Flight to the North Pole, 24 August 1949, by Francis P. Farquhar and Garfield Merner. San Francisco, CA, 1950
    - 2. Two magazine clippings
    - 3. Aircraft Magazine, (frag.), Dec, 1911
    - 4. Flying Magazine, Vol. III, No. 2., Mar, 1914
    - 5. Army and Navy News Vol. V. No. 7., Jul, 1917
  - Aeronautical notebook (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Red letter days of aviation, (2 1/4 pp), and, Some well-known aeroplanes, ms. specifications accompanied by numerous ink line-drawings. By William Lockwood Marsh.
  - Original fabric from Kitty Hawk Wright Flyer (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Gift of Lester D. Gardner. Accompanied by 2 pages of information.
  - Musee de l'Aeronautique photo postcards (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Gift of Col. W.Lockwood Marsh.
    - 1. The Breguet of Henri Bregi
    - 2. Ader's third plane
    - 3. Ader's third plane
    - 4. H. & A. Dufaux's helicopter
    - 5. The Antoinette
    - 6. Angers' plane Rene GAsnier
    - 7. Henri Farman plane, built by the Voisin brothers.
    - 8. The gyroplane Louis Breguet
    - 9. The plane in which Bleriot crossed the Channel, pictured in the Conservatoire national des arts & metiers, Paris.
    - 10. Deperdussin
    - 11. The Paul Schmitt plane.
    - 12. Works of Colonel Ch. Renard in the musee de l'aeronautique, Meudon.
    - 13. Models of observation balloons in the musee de l'aeronautique.
    - 14. Airplane models, and Fabre's hydroplane, and Breguet & Caudron's planes, together in the musee de l'aeronautique, Meudon.
    - 15. Model of the dirigeable Zodiac.
    - 16. Model of the first balloon to make a successful voyage. (Made by Pilatre of Rozier and Arlandes, 21 Nov 1783
    - 17. Twin-winged Nieuport plane.
    - 18. Model of the Voisin twin-wing.
    - 19. Model of the Santos-Dumont.
    - 20. Vapor helicopter of Ponton of Amecourt.
    - 21. The Wright motor
    - 22. The Lorraine-Dietrich motor.
    - 23. The Renault motor.
  - Lawrence Hargrave biography, December 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Memoir by A.E. Berriman, 11 typed pages inc. bibliography. Hargrave invented the box kite as well as experimenting with flight machines in general. Gift of Col. Marsh.
  - Incoming correspondence to Colonel W. Lockwood Marsh, 1921-1930 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Incoming correspondence to Colonel W. Lockwood Marsh from collectors and dealers in aeronautical materials. Gift of Col. W.L. Marsh.
    Includes a typewritten description of the G. Michelmore & Co. aeronautical collection, Aeronautica, the history of travel by balloon, told in books, autographs, pictures, and engravings, 1670-1894. (19pp)
    Also includes an excerpt sent by Roger Goodland of the Peabody Museum, An account of Nimrod's ascent towards the azure sky.
  - Miscellany from Col. W. Lockwood Marsh, Royal Aeronautical Society (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1. Programme to the garden party of the Royal Aeronautical Society, 8-May-38; (72 pp inc. many pictures)
    - 2. A History of British aeronautical periodicals, by C.G. Grey, in Aeronautics, (pp 28-36), Apr, 1944
    - 3. One flyer and one ad from the Publishers' Circular for Marsh's book, Aeronautical prints and drawings.
    - 4. Dealer's list for aeronautical material from Librairie Paul Ritti, Paris, undated; 4 pp.
  - Airplane Photographs - Aeronca Aircraft Corporation (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - American Airlines - Airglobe Magazine, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Airplane Photographs - Barnhart - Twin (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Bell Aircraft Corporation Photographs (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - U.S. Army Air Corps Beechcraft Photographs (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Consolidated Vultee Aircraft Corporation and Public Relations (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - Pictorial History of the Boeing Aircraft Company (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
  - Airplane Photographs - The Capital Airline (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Navy Parachutes (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - U.S. Navy Blimp Photographs (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Capitol Hill from the Army Air Corps Bombardment Planes photograph (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - U.S. Army Aircraft Photographs - United Aircraft Corporation (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - United Airlines School + College Service images etc. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Sikorsky Clipper, 1928-1930 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Sikorsky Clipper, 1931-1936 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Boeing Clipper, 1939-1946 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Douglas Clipper, 1937-1945 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Consolidated Clipper, 1930-1947 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Lockhead Clipper, 1934-1946 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Martin Clipper, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Republican Clipper, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Palo Alto School of Aviation pamphlet (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Navy photographs (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Army Photographs - Kellet Aircraft (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Aircraft Photographs - U.S. Military (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Douglas Airplanes (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Airplane Photographs - Delta Airlines (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Series 3. Automotive
  - Spooner + Wells Photos - Andy Albrecht Collection (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous Photos (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ladies Motor Club photographs (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Mounted prints, J.W. Debenham (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
  - England (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 2 Negatives (Safety Film) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gas Station Photograph, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Autos, Horses, and Harnessings - Ed Degner collection (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Reproduction - Charles Sykes illustration of Rolls-Royce (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photograph - 3 Automobiles; "Mrs. J. O'Hara" Written on verso (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Carriages Illustrations (Original) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Container shipping. Workers loading boxes, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series 4. Ships
  - Ship Photograph (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Ships (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Photographs and postcards depicting ships such as the Lyman Truman, Amelia, Robert Fulton, Commonwealth, City of Lowell, Priscilla, Island Queen, Creole State, Empire State Ferry San Jose, and Lord Shaftesbury/Golden Gate as well as an unidentified shipwreck and the San Francisco waterfront 1863, 1865, 1902. Photos from RJ Waters & Co., Behrman Collection, etc.
  - Shipping Lines Advertising Posters (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Berkeley Harbor, etc., circa late 30s-early 40s (Box 7, Folder 5)
    "VM341 2pi PhotoFile" and some identifications written on back. Includes shots of Martindale, New St. Joseph, Exposition King, Fishermen's Grotto.
- Series 5. Miscellaneous
  - unidentified portrait of young man in uniform [stamped Hopkins Transportation Library] (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Horses - Riding gear (Box 7, Folder 2)